[Music]
Hello there, Lar Ryan here with IELTSDaily, and today, we have a special IELTS speaking test.
We have Maddie as our examiner, who youknow very well, and we also have Julia whois an Australian native English speaker.
Who isstudying at University. And she's doing a practice IELTS speaking test today and we'll get to seewhat a native English speaker really sounds like.
[Music]
For those of you who don't know me already, my name is Lar Ryan,
and I've been an IELTS examinerfor the writing and speaking components of theIELTS test.
I've been teaching IELTS since 2010,and I have my own YouTube channel called "completetest success".
Hello and welcome to this practice exam conducted by IELTS Daily.
My name is Maddie, and I'm your practice IELTS speaking examiner.
Thequestions in this test are designed to simulate the IELTS speaking test.
Let's stop. What's yourfirst name, please? Julia. Thanks, Julia. Are you readyto begin?
Yes, I am. Let's talk about your hometown.Do you live in a city, in a town, or in the country?
So originally I'm actually from Sydney. So Sydneyis a coastal town, so it's near the beach.
So a lot of things that you can do near the beach includeswimming, you can go for walks, it's really lovely.
Um, I now actually live in Melbourne. So that's more
of a city, an urban town.
So things that you can do are shopping you can go walking again but throughthe streets, this time as a person at beach.
Um, both cities are lovely, and I'm very happy, yeah.
Now avery important part of your fluency and coherencescore is your use of discourse markers.
And whatyou may or may not have noticed is that Julia asa native English speaker, uses them a lot.
In fact,in that short answer, she used fourteen discourse markers.
So she used the word "originally". She used the word
"actually", on two occasions,
to show the examiner that they might be surprised by this information.
She used the word "so" to give herself time to think.
And she used the word "am" in the same way. She alsosaid; again, but, this time, as opposed to.
And at the end of her answer, she said yeah to indicate thatshe had finished speaking.
What is the best thing about living where you live?
I think that the best thing about where I'm living is "its proximity to the city".
So where I live is niceand close. Uh, public transport is really good.
It's very easy to get around if I ever need to getsomething or I need to do something,
it's really, really easy to do that, and I can usuallyget there in a really short period of time.
And also of course we see that she's got greatpronunciation and right at the end you hear theway she uses connected speech.
In a really sharpperiod time. The way it sounds like one very longword as opposed to many individual words.
In areally short period of time. The way the wordsconnect with each other the way she drops soundsthe way she connects sounds.
All of these features of connected speech are very very importantfor your pronunciation score and of course asa native English speaker it's very easy for
her.
But you do see the difference when youhave a candidate who is a native English speakercompared to somebody who is learning the language.
Would you like to live somewhere different Iwould definitely love to live somewhere overseas.
Um, potentially France, um, because I'm learningFrench, so it would be lovely to be able topractice my French and experience anotherculture and get to know a whole new group of people.
I think that would be really cool.I'd like to move on to the topic of jokes.
Are you good at remembering jokes? No. Um, I, I'mnot very good at reading jokes I'm not gonna lie.
Um, something my dad always loved to tell jokes,and I think that because he loved jokes so much.
I always became deterred from them. Um, typical dad
jokes, um, but yeah. What type of jokes do you like?
I think that I usually prefer the types of jokesthat more like riddles or they have sort of astory to them.
So you get invested in the story,and it goes on for a while, and then you havethe punch line at the end.
That's the sort of jokethat I prefer. Um, as opposed to the short, witty jokes.
Okay, now, after listening to Julie give a few moreanswers, what you probably notice is that she isnot flawless.
She needs to stop. She needs to pause.She needs to think.
Sometimes she's not completelyflawless in the way you would find when you'rewatching a TV show or a movie.
Where the whole dialogue is scripted, and the actors are repeating what they've learned.
So in the real world, English speaking is not as flawless as you see on TV.
So, what we see from Julia here is exactly what theexaminer is looking for when someone's going to achieve a band nine.
Do you enjoy watching comedyshows on TV? I do. I enjoy watching comedy shows onTV.
I also actually went to a comedy show about twonights ago.
Which was really fun to watch, reallyinteresting to see, um, some people live speaking.
Um, definitely, the "standard of comedy" was verydifferent between the professionals on comedyshows and a local comedy stand-up competition.
Um, "but nonetheless," it was really enjoyable.
Now let's think about the topic of gardening. Doyou have a garden where you live?
I actually live in an apartment, so I don't have a garden.
However,we do have a large balcony, and on the balcony, wehave lots of plants. There's a veggie garden.
Um,most of the plants are in pots, um, and it's quite nice because I have two dogs. So they love torun around and... frolic near the plants, I guess.
Okay, so we've pretty much watched all of her partone answers already, and you might be thinking wellJulia's vocabulary isn't that great.
I know most ofthis vocabulary myself already, so why is she goingto get such a high score with vocabulary thatI know.
The reality is when you're in the IELTStest, you're not trying to use vocabulary thatnobody knows.
You're trying to use vocabulary thateverybody knows.
Using normal everyday vocabularyis what will get you a high score.
But it's usingit accurately and using it in the correct context.
And then, for whatever topic that you're discussing,having that specific topic-related language thatwill show that you have a wide range is what getsyou a high score.
So if you've been learningspecial words for the IELTS test that you think are impressive and that will get you a highscore,
what you see from Julia's performance hereis that, that is not what the examiner is actuallylooking for.
And do you like gardening? I do likegardening actually.
Um, because we have the veggie patch. Ireally enjoy planting different vegetables.
Um, I often do this with my mum becauseshe's "very passionate about cooking",and using different vegetables and herbs.
Um, soquite often, I will help her out there. Um, yeah.
And do you know anyone else who does a lotof gardening? My grandmother loves gardening.
She has a really, really "large property", and thereare lots of different plants, and again, she hasa veggie patch.
And she spends "almost all dayevery day" out in the garden, gardening.
Using all sorts of different tools and plantingdifferent vegetables.
And similar to my mum, she likes to use the, the vegetables that sheplants and that she grows and she uses themto cook.
Which is, which I think is really cool. Would you like to have a big garden in the future?
I think I would like to have a big garden in thefuture. Um, "there's something really nice about" beingaround nature and around plants.
And again thataspect of the veggie garden is something that Ireally like, and I would like to incorporate thatinto my home when I'm older and in the future.
Another important aspect of your pronunciationscore is that you use intonation correctly.
And, of course, as a native English speaker, Julia is doingthis.
So one thing that you may notice is when she's speaking, if she's not finished yet she'llgo up.
So if there's going to be a pause, she goes up.
That will indicate to the examiner that she'snot finished yet she'll say some more,
and then she says some more, and then at the end, when she'sfinished, she goes down.
If you pay attention to that you'll notice how she's communicating withher intonation as well as with her vocabulary.
Part two in the next part of the test I'mgoing to give you a topic, and I would likeyou to speak on this for one to two minutes.
You will have one minute to think about whatyou want to say, and I will give you a pen andsome paper to make notes if you want.
Is that clear? Yes. So here is your pen, and here'syour paper, you have one minute to prepare.
Thank you. Now I would like you to talk aboutthe first phone you had.
Remember you have oneto two minutes for this, so don't worry ifI stop you.
I'll tell you when the time is up. Can you start speaking now please? Okay, so thefirst phone that I owned was when I was in year six.
It was actually a gift from my godmotherfor my birthday, and it was a pink Nokia flip phone.
And I remember when I first got it, I wasso happy because it was my first phone, and Icould call and text my friends,
and it was reallyexciting, um, and the phone had "a cool retro design".
Um, and so I loved my phone so much and I used
it all the time.
Um, and then I remember as the iPhone came out, all of my friends in year sixwere getting iPhones, "which was ridiculous" nowthat I look back at it.
But I remember being sojealous of all my friends who had this.
These "groovy cutting-edge iPhones" with touchscreens. Um, and I had my little cute retro Nokia.
Um, but I look back at it, and I almost want to havea Nokia here again now. I kind of miss my phone.
Um, because I think it was just really nice tobe able to focus just on contacting friends,
and I think that's what phones originally that'swhat their purpose was.
You couldn't contact anyone from anywhere and just stay in contact andconnected with everyone, and I kind of missed thataspect.
I think that phones are very convenientnow but I think there's almost too many thingsthat you can do on a phone.
Um, so yeah "I think it would always be nice to" have the technology revert a little bit and go back in time a littlebit.
Um, and get back to those, to those basics, yeah.
Um, yeah, so I think that if I had my timeagain I would have kept my, my originalNokia phone for as long as possible.
Um, andI'm glad that my parents did keep me withthe same phone for the following, I think twoor three years. Um, so yeah. Thank you. No worries.
Okay, I'm sure you noticed that at one minuteand 40 seconds, Julia had no idea what to saynext.
She pretty much concluded her answer, butthen even though we couldn't see Maddie on camera,
we're pretty sure she did something like this, toindicate to Julia that the time wasn't up and sheneeded to stay speaking.
And this shows us just howhard it really is to continue speaking on a topicfor a full two minutes.
So if it's difficult fora native English speaker in their own language, ofcourse, it's going to be challenging for youas well in a second language.
So do lots of preparation for IELTS speaking part two.
Makesure you've prepared yourself by practicingmany, many different topics, many different parttwo cue cards,
and getting comfortable with the note-taking process in the one minute to makenotes.
So that you can comfortably continuespeaking for a full two minutes when you'rein your IELTS speaking test.
Now part three. I wanna stay on the topic of communication.
Has our ability to communicate with each other improved over the last fifty years.
I think this is aninteresting question because I think that obviously, it has with the increaseof technology.
So what I was saying before about how we can, you know, contact people, mobilephones, we can send messages, we can send photos.
Um, things like FaceTime and video chat makeit really accessible to contact people whenyou're not physically with them.
Having said that"when you are not physically with people" I think ourability to communicate has actually decreased.
Because we lose those skills when we becomeso used to contacting people exclusively viatechnology you do lose that capacity to havereal meaningful connections face to face.
So Ithink that that's definitely something a way thatour communication has actually, um reduced.
Yeah.And can body language help you communicate better?
Yes, definitely. Um, and this sort of flows on fromthat idea about face-to-face communication.
Um, because when obviously, when you contact people through aphone or through a computer, it's very difficult tosense their body language.
Um, so being in person andbeing able to read people's body language and, youknow, get vibes, I guess, from people, you couldsay.
It's really, really important it's reallydifficult to achieve that through technology.
Andif you were having a difficult conversation withsomeone, would you prefer to have it over the phoneor in person.
I would always prefer to have thosesorts of conversations in person because I thinkit really is important to sort of connect with theother person.
In terms of seeing like visually howthey're reacting and be able to sort of match my...
My reactions and my communication styles to howthat other person is feeling.
So that you can both"be on the same page" and you can adjust becausethose things you just couldn't do via text or call.
Right, so after listening to quite a few of Julia'spart three answers, what we notice is that she'sreally good at developing them.
She answers thequestion and then she goes into more detail.
She never gives short answers, and then, on the otherside is she doesn't stay going on forever and everso that the examiner has to interrupt her.
Juliagives a nice amount of development. Enough that theanswer is strongly supported and then she finisheswaits for the next question and starts again.
And why is it important to understandhow different cultures communicate
I think it's really important because aswe've seen through the increasive technology communication within a single culture canchange so much over a period of time.
So... and so, seeing how different culturesvary in terms of communication style,
It just shows you that it's really, really necessary to appreciate and understand how thosevariations are sort of crucial to understandingthe cultures, of course, but then also understandingcommunication itself.
Because there is such avast variety and there is no right or wrong way.
Thank you. That is the end of this practice IELTS
speaking test. Thank you. So, Julia, how is thatfor you.
That was good I think, um, I really likedthe questions actually I thought it were reallyinteresting topics and I think it went prettywell.
And did you find any of the questions hard?
I actually found the gardening questions difficult,ironically.
Um, because I think it's difficult to elaborate on questions that are quite specific,so yeah. And did you make any noticeable mistakes?
Um, I think, as opposed to grammatical mistakes Ithink there were definitely a few times where Isort of went in circlesand rambled on a little bit.
Um, but yeah. Do you remember any of the questionsand if you do, can you remind us what they were.
Because, sometimes, after an exam, it is reallyhard to remember what questions you were asked.
Um, "to the best of my memory," the exam started withquestions about my hometown and where I lived.
Um, that was followed by a question about whetheror not I liked where I lived I'm pretty sure.
Um, and then there were questions about gard... IfI had a garden. If I do gardening, um, and thenif anyone I know does a lot of gardening.
And Ithink that was followed by the question about...
Um, my first phone, and then after that,was about communication styles and theimportance of body language.
And whether ornot we need to appreciate and accept and understand communication styles from differentcultures.
Um, yeah. Well done. You just missed out on the jokes topic. Which talked about jokes? Doyou like jokes? What TV shows do you watch?
And, um, what kind of jokes you actually like? Of course.
Okay, so we've seen a lot of great language from Julia.
I really enjoyed listening to her answersmyself and I hope you did as well.
Now it's time to give her her scores, and this is an incrediblyeasy task for me or for any IELTS examiner, and I'm sure you would agree on these scores.
Fluency andcoherence is a band nine, lexical resource is a band nine, grammatical range and accuracy is band nine, and of course pronunciation nine.
Overall, band nine great performances but of courseshe's a native English speaker, so it is not thatsurprising.
If you are aiming for a high scoreyourself hopefully you've learned some things from Julia's performance, and you can put thoseinto action as well.
Let us know in the comments what did you learn from watching Julie perform andwhat did you enjoy about listening to her answers.
Hello, and welcome to this practice exam conductedby IELTS Daily. My name is Maddie, and I'm yourpractice IELTS speaking examiner.
The questionsin this test are designed to simulate the IELTSspeaking test.
Let's start. What's your firstname, please? Julia. Thanks, Julia are you readyto begin.
Yes, I am. Let's talk about your hometown.Do you live in a city in a town or in the country?
So originally I'm actually from Sydney. So Sydneyis a coastal town so it's near the beach.
So a lot of things that you can do near the beach includeswimming, you can go for walks it's really lovely.
Um, I now actually live in Melbourne. So that's more ofa city an urban town so things that you can do areshopping.
Uh, you can go walking again, but throughthe streets, this time as a person at a beach. Bothcities are lovely, and I'm very happy. Yeah.
Whatis the best thing about living where you live?
I think that the best thing about where I'm livingis its proximity to the city. So, where I live isnice and close.
Uh, public transport is really good.It's very easy to get around if I ever need to getsomething or I need to do something.
It's reallyreally easy to do that, and I can usually get therein a really short period of time.
Would you liketo live somewhere different?
I would definitely love to live somewhere overseas, um, potentiallyFrance. Um, because I'm learning French.
So it would be lovely to be able to practice my French andexperience another culture and get to know a whole new group of people.
I think that would be reallycool. I'd like to move on to the topic of jokes.
Are you good at remembering jokes. No, um, I, I'mnot very good at remembering jokes I'm not gonna lie.
Um, something my dad always loved to tell jokes. Um,and I think that because he loved jokes so much, I always became deterred from them.
Um, typical dadjokes, um, but yeah. What type of jokes do you like?
I think that I usually prefer the types of jokesthat more like riddles or they have sort of astory to them.
So you get invested in the story,and it goes on for a while, and then you have thepunch line at the end.
That's sort of joke thatI prefer, as opposed to the short witty jokes.
Do you enjoy watching comedy shows on TV? I do. Ienjoy watching comedy shows on TV.
I also actually went to a comedy show about two nights ago, whichwas really fun to watch. Really interesting to see.
Um, some people live speaking. Um, definitely thestandard of Comedy was very different between the professionals on comedy shows and a localcomedy stand-up competition.
Um, but nonetheless, it was really enjoyable. Now let's think about thetopic of gardening. Do you have a garden whereyou live?
I actually live in an apartment, so Idon't have a garden however, we do have a large balcony, and on the balcony, we have lots ofplants there's a veggie garden.
Um, most of the plants are in pots, and it's quite nice becauseI have two dogs, so they love to run around and...
Frolic near the plants, I guess, and do youlike gardening? I do like gardening, actually.
Um, because we have the veggie patch. I really enjoyplanting different vegetables.
Um, I often do this with my mum because she's very passionate about cookingand using different vegetables and herbs.
So quite often, I will help her out there, um, yeah. And do youknow anyone else who does a lot of gardening.
My grandmother loves gardening. She has areally really large property.
And there are lots of different plants and again she hasa veggie patch and she spends almost all day every day out in the garden, gardening.
Um, usingall sorts of different tools and planting different vegetables,
and similar to my momshe likes to use the, the vegetables that sheplants and that she grows, and she uses themto cook
Which is, which I think is really cool.
Would you like to have a big Garden in thefuture? I think I would like to have a big garden in the future.
Um, there's something really nice aboutbeing around nature and around plants.
And again, that aspect of the veggie garden is something thatI really like, and I would like to incorporate thatinto my home when I'm older and in the future.
Parttwo. In the next part of the test, I'm going to giveyou a topic, and I would like you to speak on thisfor one to two minutes.
You will have one minute to think about what you want to say, and I willgive you a pen and some paper to make notes ifyou want.
Is that clear? Yes. So, here is your pen, andhere's your paper you have one minute to prepare.
Thank you. Now, I would like you to talk about
the first phone you had.
Remember you have oneto two minutes for this, so don't worry ifI stop you. I'll tell you when the time is up.
Can you start speaking now, please? Okay, so thefirst phone that I owned was when I was in yearsix.
It was actually a gift from my godmotherfor my birthday and it was a pink Nokia flipphone.
And I remember when I first got it, I wasso happy because it was my first phone and I could call and text my friends, and it was reallyexciting.
Um, and the phone had a cool retro design.
Um, and so I loved my phone so much, and I used
it all the time.
Um, and then I remember as the iPhone came out all of my friends in year sixwere getting iPhones which was ridiculous nowthat I look back at it.
But I remember being sojealous of all my friends who had this thesegroovy Cutting Edge iPhones with touchscreens.
Um, and I had my little cute retro Nokia.
Um, but I look back at it, and I almost want to havea Nokia here again now.
I kind of miss my phone, um, because I think it was just really nice tobe able to focus just on contacting friends.
And I think that's what phones originally that'swhat their purpose was. You couldn't contactanyone from anywhere and just stay in contact andconnected with everyone.
And I kind of missed that aspect. I think that phones are very convenientnow, but I think there's almost too many things that you can do on a phone.
Um, so yeah, I thinkit would always be nice to have the technologyrevert a little bit.
And go back in time a littlebit um and get back to those to those basics, yeah.
Um, yeah so I think that if I had my time again I would have kept my, my original Nokia phone for as long as possible.
Um, andI'm glad that my parents did keep me with the same phone for the following, I think, twoor three years. Um, so yeah. Thank you. No worries.
Now part three. I want to stayon the topic of communication.
Has our ability to communicate with eachother improved over the last fifty years.
I think this is an interesting question becauseI think that obviously, it has with the increaseof technology.
So what I was saying beforeabout how we can you know contact peopleon mobile phones.
We can send messages, we can sendphotos, things like FaceTime, and video chat makes it really accessible to contact people whenyou're not physically with them.
Having said that when you are physically with people Ithink our ability to communicate has actuallydecreased.
Because we lose those skills when webecome so used to contacting people exclusivelyvia technology.
You do lose that capacity tohave real, meaningful connections face-to-face.
Um, so I think that that's definitely somethinga way that our communication has actually...
Um, reduced, yeah. And, can bodylanguage help you communicate better?
Yes, definitely, um, and this sort of flows on fromthat idea about face-to-face communication.
Um, because when obviously, when you contact people through aphone or through a computer, it's very difficult to sense that body language.
Um, so being in person andbeing able to read people's body language and, you know, get vibes I guess from people you couldsay.
It's really, really important. It's really difficult to achieve that through technology.
Andif you were having a difficult conversation withsomeone, would you prefer to have it over the phoneor in person.
I would always prefer to have those sorts of conversations in person because I thinkit really is important to sort of connect with theother person.
In terms of seeing like visually how they're reacting and be able to sort of match my...
My reactions and my communication styles to howthat other person is feeling.
So that you can both be on the same page and you can adjust becausethose things you just couldn't do via text or call
And why is it important to understandhow different cultures communicate?
I think it's really important because aswe've seen through the increasive technology,communication within a single culture canchange so much over a period of time.
So, and so seeing how different culturesvary in terms of communication style,
it just shows you that it's really, reallynecessary to appreciate and understand how those variations are sort of crucial to understandingthe cultures,
of course, but then also understandingcommunication itself.
Because there is such a vastvariety and there is no right or wrong way.
Thank you, that is the end of this practice IELTS
speaking test. Thank you.
So, Julia, how is that for you. That was good, I think, um, I really likedthe questions actually, I thought it were really interesting topics and I think it went prettywell.
And did you find any of the questions hard?
I actually found the gardening questions difficultironically, um, because I think it's difficult to elaborate on questions that are quite specificso yeah.
And did you make any noticeable mistakes?
Um, I think, as opposed to grammatical mistakes Ithink there were definitely a few times where I sort of went in circlesand rambled on a little bit.
Um, but yeah. Do you remember any of the questionsand if you do can you remind us what they were,
because sometimes after an exam it is reallyhard to remember what questions you were asked.
Um, to the best of my memory, the exam started with
questions about my hometown and where I lived. I'm pretty sure.
Um, that was followed by a question about whetheror not I liked where I lived I'm pretty sure.
Um, and then there were questions aboutgard, if I had a garden. If I do gardening.
Um, and then if anyone Iknow does a lot of gardening.
And I think that was followed by the questionabout um my first phone and then after that wasabout communication styles,
and the importanceof body language and whether or not we needto appreciate and accept,
and understandcommunication styles from different cultures.
Um, yeah well done. You just missed out on the jokestopic. Which talked about jokes. Do you like jokes?
What TV shows do you watch, and, um, what kind of
jokes you actually like?
Great, well I'm sure Chris will have some more in-depth feedback for you,and thank you so much. Fabulous, thank you.
[Music]